<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sir Barnabas Scvdamore's defence Vindicating him from those grand inputations o[f] treachery and negligence, in the late surprisall of Hereford, vvhich through the ignorance of some, and malice of others, are unjustly layd upon him. Also, discovering the true causes and maner of its surprisall the 18. day of September, anno Domini 1645.</title>
            <author>Scudamore, Barnabas, Sir, d. 1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92761</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2129A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R231548</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896837</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896837</idno>
            <idno type="VID">137065</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92761)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 137065)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2448:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sir Barnabas Scvdamore's defence Vindicating him from those grand inputations o[f] treachery and negligence, in the late surprisall of Hereford, vvhich through the ignorance of some, and malice of others, are unjustly layd upon him. Also, discovering the true causes and maner of its surprisall the 18. day of September, anno Domini 1645.</title>
                  <author>Scudamore, Barnabas, Sir, d. 1658.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 23, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare 1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing CD-ROM, 1996.</note>
                  <note>DFo copy, reel 2448, is trimmed affecting text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scudamore, Barnabas, --  Sir, d. 1658 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Hereford (England) --  History --  Siege, 1645 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:137065:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:137065:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SIR BARNABAS SCVDAMORE. DEFENCE.</p>
            <p>Vindicating him from thoſe grand imputations Treachery and Negligence, in the late Surpriſall of <hi>Hereford,</hi> VVhich through the ignorance of ſome, and malice of others are unjuſtly layd upon him.</p>
            <p>ALSO, Diſcovering the true Cauſes and Maner of its Surpriſall the 18. day of <hi>September, Anno Domini</hi> 1645.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare 1646.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="defense">
            <pb facs="tcp:137065:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:137065:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Sir</hi> Barnabas Scudamore's <hi>Defence.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HO commands in chiefe, in any kinde of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, becomes the ſingle ſubject of all great faylings; when in ſucceſſe, Officers and Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, expect the benefit of it. This being my caſe in the ſurpriſall of <hi>Hereford,</hi> the 18. of <hi>December</hi> 1645. is aggravated upon me (with ſuch a kinde of Treachery and wilfull Negligence) that could the charge be made good againſt me, would render mee not only unfit for imployment, but for life. The importance of this Town, at that time, to the King, my Maſter, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever depended on him, was not unknowne unto me; And when I have ſayd this, I have ſaydenough, to ſhew the degree and odiouſneſſe of ſuch a villany. Yet Paſſing by (that which is obvious) the blemiſhing of that honourable Profeſſion of a Soldier (whoſe proper Acts ate the defence of Iuſtice) and the ſtayning of the Family whereof I am deſcended; I will adde this, that to betray thoſe perſons, and that Towne unto plunder and ſlaughter, in whoſe defence my duty and love did reſolve me rather to die, had beene an act unchriſtian and moſt barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous. Yet under the oppreſſion of this reſtleſſe charge, I have layne languiſhing a Priſoner at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> ſeven months. My importunity for a triall at a Court of VVarre, hath beene with; out ceaſing. Twice or thrice it pleaſed his Maieſty to write tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:137065:3"/>
I ſhould be tranſported to <hi>Oxford.</hi> But malice hath beene no leſſe buſie to keepe me both from that, and all trialls, then it was to aſperſe me at firſt. <hi>Oxford</hi> being rendred to the Parliament, and <hi>Worceſter</hi> likely to follow, I laboured the Governour of this latter place, to graunt me a publike hearing there; which yet I failed to obtaine, with effect, through the abſence of the ſaid Governour from the Court of VVarre; though the time and place, and ſummoning of all witneſſes were fixed upon ſeverall publique poſts by his appointment. Soone after, <hi>Worceſter</hi> being in the ſame condition with <hi>Oxford,</hi> and my marching away in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded with the reſt, and my liberty a conſequent thereof, I ſee not now any other meanes left to vindicate my ſelfe from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach with the world (ſince I know not when I may be ſo happy as to come to a judiciall triall) then, according to the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved example of perſons in like caſes, to publiſh a true relation of the whole buſineſſe: and therefore <hi>I</hi> ſhall endeavour without partiality to repreſent the motions, and naked ſtate, of the whole, as it was carried, poynt by poynt, from the beginning.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>John Bridges</hi> being diſcontented for the burning of his Houſe, and for ſome reproachfull Language given him by one of his Majeſties Generalls, upon the buſineſſe of the Clubmen: and angry with me, for not having ſomething that he deſired, which yet <hi>I</hi> could not give him; quits the Kings Quarters, and goes to <hi>Glouceſter;</hi> where, and in the parts adjacent, reſiding ſome two or three Monthes, and comming ſometimes into <hi>Hereford-ſhire</hi> in diſguiſe, the better to lay his deſigne, at length goes up to <hi>London,</hi> and preſents to the Committees of both Kingdomes, Propoſitions for the taking of <hi>Hereford,</hi> by the way of <hi>Stratagem,</hi> as he calls it. Hereupon Order is given to Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:137065:3"/>
               <hi>Birch,</hi> then Governour of <hi>Bath,</hi> to joyne his forces with Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell <hi>Morgan,</hi> Governour of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> for the purpoſe aforſaid.</p>
            <p>Coll. <hi>Birch,</hi> his forces being joyned accordingly, comes pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately, with Sir <hi>Iohn Bridges</hi> from <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> to a place ſome few miles from <hi>Hereford,</hi> where they met with two perſons (that is as I am credibly enformed, Cap. <hi>Howorth,</hi> and Cap. <hi>Alderne</hi>) both Captaines under the King; by whom Coll. <hi>Birch</hi> (as in his prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Letter may appeare) was ſufficiently informed of the ſtate of the Towne; and returning backe to Gloceſter, they received continuall intelligence of the condition of Hereford, by the meanes of the ſaid Captaine <hi>Howorth</hi> and Captaine <hi>Alderne,</hi> but eſpecially from Captaine <hi>Ballard</hi> my Captaine Lieutenant; up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whoſe advertiſements, being now drawne into their party, they moſt relyed. In few dayes after, theſe aforeſaid two Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nells marched with all their forces to <hi>Ledbury,</hi> in the County of <hi>Hereford;</hi> where they arrived at five a clocke in the evening, upon Munday the 15. of December. Notice whereof being ſent mee, the next morning very early from one at <hi>Ledbury,</hi> upon whom I depended conſtantly for intelligence, I diſpatched the meſſenger backe with directions, that freſh meſſengers ſhould be ſent, to and fro continually, to adviſe me of the poſture and motion of the Enemy. I likewiſe diſpatched inſtantly Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes, to intimate the ſame to Sir <hi>Michael Woodhouſe,</hi> Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Ludlow,</hi> and Sir <hi>William Vaughan,</hi> who lay at <hi>Bridgenorth,</hi> collecting forces for the reliefe of <hi>Cheſter.</hi> And I gave immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate order to Captaine <hi>Chaplaine,</hi> the Towne-Major, to double the Guards in the Towne. And the Towne being weakned by forces ſent forth two dayes before, for the reliefe of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving drawne in, the day before, all the Horſe that were quarte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:137065:4"/>
in the Country (ſaving the Lieutenant Colonells Troop) for the better fortifying of the Garriſon, upon this notice of the advance of the Enemy, <hi>I</hi> drew in his Troope alſo; giving him command to guard that night, and to ſend out of the Towne at Port-ſhutting a party of his Horſe to guard without, and petroll toward the Enemy, to guard within, and goe the Grand-Round himſelfe; to goe forth likewiſe himſelfe at Port-opening, the next morning with Horſe as farre as <hi>Lug-bridge:</hi> all which the ſaid Lieutenant colonell <hi>Ieffreys</hi> did exactly performe. This Troop was no ſooner in, but, though it were drawne in upon this cauſe, a company of Townſmen take occaſion from hence to raiſe a mutiny; and ſo, while we ſhould have beene in attendance to the motions of the Enemy without, the towneſmen refuſing quarter to this troope, and towneſmen and ſouldiers going to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether by the ears, and the countenance of the mutiny appearing as if it were like to grow to a very great height, worke &amp; difficulty I had enough; yea, I was wholly imployed to ſuppreſſe the muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny within. VVhether this was done upon deſigne or no, I cannot ſay; but I have inducements to thinke it ſo. Sure I am, the notice of it gave incouragement to the Enemy: Of whoſe march, all Munday night from <hi>Ledbury</hi> toward <hi>Hereford,</hi> as far as <hi>Cannon-Froom,</hi> I had notice by divers upon Tueſday mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; as likewiſe upon Tueſday night, of their returne backe to <hi>Ledbury.</hi> Vpon VVedneſday in the afternoone, I was advertiſed that the enemy was marched out of <hi>Ledbury,</hi> and that the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the common Souldier in <hi>Ledbury</hi> was, that they were going towards <hi>Hereford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:137065:4"/>This newes the Meſſenger delivering privately by word of mouth, when Maſter <hi>Major,</hi> and ſome halfe a ſcore Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen and Townes-men were in the roome with me, I did inſtantly communicate it in publique to them all. And di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected Maſter <hi>Major</hi> to make Proclamation; that the Towns<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men might have notice of this intelligence: And withall, he required preſently to ſhovell off the Snow from the Walls, that the place might be fit for them to ſtand on with their Armes upon the firſt Alarum; which Proclamation was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly made. At two of the Clocke, the ſaid afternoone, Order was given by me, to Livetenant Colonell <hi>Jeffreys,</hi> who commanded the Horſe in chiefe, that as he, in his owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon had performed the duty of the Guards the night before, as is before expreſſed, ſo he ſhould give Order, that the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, who had the Guard that Wedneſday night, ſhould doe the very ſame. This Order Livetenant Colonell <hi>Ieffreys</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth to have received from me; and affirmes, that he tranſmitted it to Major <hi>Fletcher;</hi> who by turne had the command of the Guard that Wedneſday night; and Major <hi>Fletcher</hi> under his hand, hath acknowledged that he received the ſaid Orders from Livetenant Colonell <hi>Ieffreys;</hi> But the next daies ſucceſſe doth manifeſt, that no Horſe were ſent out that night, and that Major <hi>Fletcher</hi> failed in that important du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            <p>About three a clock, that afternoone, I gave Major <hi>Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine</hi> Orders to double the Guards: Which he performed not, as by the liſt he gave me appeares. At nine a clock, I diſmiſt the ſaid <hi>Chaplaine</hi> to goe to his reſt; telling him, that I would goe the grand round my ſelfe; and ſhould expect
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:137065:5"/>
him to be with me at five a clock in the morning, to receive from me the defects of the Guards and to looke to the Towne, while I might catch an houres reſt or two; being, at eight a clock in the morning, to ſit at a Court of Warre, upon the Mutineers of the day before. The grand round I went about one of the clock, and beginning at the maine Guard, I found that Captaine <hi>Traherne,</hi> Captaine of the Watch, was not upon the place; and reſenting it, I directed his Enſigne to ſend for him, in my name, to attend his duty: which was done accordingly, but <hi>Traherne</hi> came not. Going on the round, at every Port, I charged them, upon paine of death, that neither Officer, nor Souldier, ſhould ſtirre off from their Guard; ever adding, that the enemie was advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, and the Towne in danger. Comming to <hi>Byſters Gate,</hi> at which Port they that come from <hi>Ledbury</hi> enter, and where indeed the enemy did enter, I found the Corporall ſo drunke that he could not give me the word, whom I corrected for the preſent with my Cane, and commanded my Captaine, Livetenant, the above mentioned <hi>Ballard,</hi> who commanded the round with me, (mine owne Company being upon the Guard) to place an Officer in Commiſſion at that Port, as ſoone as the grand round ſhould be ended, and to lay the Corporall by the heeles. Looking up I called to the Sentinel that ſtood on the top of that Gate, to ſwingle his match; and anſwer being made, that he had a ſnap-hanz, for the more ſurety, I ſent another Souldier up and called him downe, and finding it to be ſo, and fixt, and laden, I returned him up to his ſentry place and added one more to him; leaving a ſtrict charge, that the Sentries ſhould be often viſited, and relie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:137065:5"/>
every halfe houre. So that whereas it is noyſed, that I called downe this Sentry, and returned none up, to meet with this rumor, you may perceive, that inſtead of one I placed there two. And here, ſeeing it is in my way, let me anſwer another as frivolous objection. It is bruited abroad, that I gave money to corrupt the Guard. Tis true, that as I paſſed by the Ports, I gave in that cold ſnowie night, ſome twelvepence, or eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen pence a peece, as my cuſtome was, to each Guard; yet with order to the Officer, who received that money from me, that they ſhould not drinke it till nine a clock; and five ſhillings I gave to the Officer of the Horſe, with like order. But at this Port (<hi>Byſters Gate</hi>) finding things as you ſee not in order I gave not one penny. The grand round being ended, about five of the clock I commanded my Captaine Livetenant <hi>Ballard</hi> to continue rounds without ceaſing, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till eigh, tand to give me an account. Which Order he altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neglected, though I did not only give it him at the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſing of the Guards; but afterwards, at mine owne houſe, repeating it twice at leaſt: Yea, it was the laſt word I ſaid unto him. But it is no wonder, if we conſider what doth fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low: For in place of it, tis very well knowne, by teſtimony of ſome who entred the Towne with the enemie, that he the ſaid <hi>Ballard</hi> drew off the Guards from <hi>Byſters Gate;</hi> where, when the Towne was entred, were but foure Souldiers. And further, that he had beforehand poyſoned, or by ſome other meanes, diſabled the Murthering Peece, which lay in the mouth of <hi>Byſters Gate.</hi> Both which good Officers were faire preparatives for the force which was without to enter with greater eaſe and ſafetie. But where is Major <hi>Chaplaine,</hi> the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:137065:6"/>
Towne Major, whom the Common Councell ſome weekes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore recommended to me for that place with much impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity. It is not unknowne, I then told them, that he would deceive them, and would not riſe in a morning. And now they find my words made good: For according to Order I expected him to take the charge of the Towne as befitted his Office; yea, I enquired often for him not without paſſion; but then no newes could be heard of him: Yet now in his confeſſion, under his hand, he is not aſhamed to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vow, that he was in his bed when the Towne was taken, which was about eight a clock in the morninge. And though his nature may incline ſome to thinke that this was ſloth; and others, through his report, that the woundes which he had in his body, and the attendance of the Chyrurgion to dreſſe it, may be the matter; yet I doubt there was a worſe thing in it. For cleerely, the wound that troubled him, for it is but one, is but in the nature of an Iſſue, and requires but the atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of an Iſſue. Beſides, this wound hath been in him ſome yeares; and notwithſtanding it, during the ſiege of <hi>Hereford,</hi> which was not above foure moneths before, he was able to watch all night, and doe his duty all day, taking his reſt but as other Officers did. But ſuppoſe him to be generally unable to riſe betimes; yet when that Towne which recommended him to, the place was in danger, and the Governour, by expreſſe Order had commanded him to be with him by five in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; and at a time, when all the Towne knew, by Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that the enemy was approaching: For him then not to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of himſelfe to riſe two or three houres before his accuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomed time, but to ſleepe, ſecure, doth ſhrewdly infer his minde
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:137065:6"/>
to be in a worſe condition then his body. But ſleep he did not all this while; he was awake earely enough, yea too ſoon in that reſpect. For his Lieut: <hi>Cooper</hi> ſpake with him that morning, and received from his hands the keyes of the ſally Ports of the Caſtle: with which keyes, for my part, I know not what Major <hi>Chaplaine</hi> did. But Lieu: <hi>Lightfoot,</hi> to whoſe cuſtody theſe keyes did properly belong, informes, that this <hi>Chaplaine,</hi> that night in my name (and I ſay again with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out my knowledge) demanded the Keyes of him, as ſent for by me, and got them from him by much importunity. Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible enough it is, that through theſe Sally-ports the enemy received intelligence that night and morning: for it is moſt certaine, they expected intelligence out of the Towne, even to the very minute of their entrance, in caſe any difficulty ſhould have riſen unexpectedly, to ſecure themſelves. But <hi>Cooper</hi> finding me gone to reſt, thought likely the time to be now moſt fit, and finding the Salli-port keyes to be of no further uſe for his deſigne in hand, to conceale himſelfe, rids his hands of thoſe keyes to Lieutenant <hi>Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot,</hi> as returned by his Major; and then comes inſtantly to my houſe, and demands and preſſes with great importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to have the keyes of the great Gates delivered him, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending that carts and people ſtaied in the ſtreet to go forth; which though it might have a colorable ſhew was far from truth. But his earneſtneſſe at length prevailed with him that waited in my chamber to ſteale up that he might not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake mee, and to take the keyes which were in the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:137065:7"/>
(and ſo ſtill in my ſight being awake) and to bring them downe to him.</p>
            <p>The keyes received, away he haſtens, and omitting the ordinary duties, which were to go to the main Guard, and take a guard with him, ſends the other keyes to their ſeverall Ports, and paſſing to Byſters gate, opens not the wicket, ſends out no Scouts, but opens the great Gate, lets downe the great Chaine, lets fall the Draw-bridge, and going over himſelfe, while he ſaw upon the ſide of the Mote the Liev. and ſix ſouldiers, who acted the part of the Conſtable and Labourers (whoſe reported pretence of being ſent for by warrant) <hi>Cooper</hi> could not but know to be untrue, for hee was the overſeer of the VVorks, &amp; writ all ſuch VVarrants, and ſaw the ſnow upon the ground which made it unfit for work, and knew that the Ice was every day broken by the Garriſon, cryes out (and to them certainly) <hi>Now or Never, Now or Never.</hi> And happily thinking it would be too hot for him to returne the ſame way he went forth, runs amaine along the ditch ſide, and comes backe into the Towne at the Caſtle; which very returne into the Towne, when hee could not but ſee as hee ran along the Enemy entring, ſhewes that he had a greater confidence in them, then one true to the Garriſon could have.</p>
            <p>VVith this the Enemy enters, the above mentioned per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Captaine <hi>Howorth</hi> being in the forelorne-hope of foot that ſeconded the ſaid perſonated Conſtable and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers: Sir <hi>Iohn Bridges</hi> in the forelorne-hope of Horſe,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:137065:7"/>
and Captaine <hi>Aldern</hi> in the ſecond diviſion. Being entred the Gate, where they found but foure Souldiers, the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorne-hope of Horſe, takes the right hand, and ſeizeth upon the Maine-guards, where were but ſix Souldiers and one Enſigne; And Captaine <hi>Alderne,</hi> my profeſſed Enemy, takes the left hand to my houſe and the Caſtle. My man brings word to my bed-ſide the Enemy was entered. I leapt up, commanded him to get me a horſe, and ſlipping on my cloathes, I ran inſtantly downe with my Sword and Piſtoll in my hand, to the fore gate towards the ſtreet, where the Enemies Horſe already come fired upon me, and ſhot my Secretary into the belly. At which I retreating, another of the houſe, ſhuts the door, &amp; out I got at a back way towards the River, in hopes ſtill of my horſe. Vpon the left hand, at the Caſtle, I was ſhewed the Enemy gallopping towards me; upon the right hand, going to the Biſhops Pallace, I found a body of their foot comming into the Pallace yard: and ſeeing my ſelfe thus beſet, my boy ſhewing mee that a couple were gotten to the other ſide of the River over the Ice, by which I perceived it would beare; I paſſed over, and got to the gate at <hi>Wybridge,</hi> where intending to get into the Towne at the wicket, I ſaw moſt of the guard gone, and a body of their horſe comming upon the Bridge; and then, underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Enemy to be fully poſſeſſed of the Towne, and no poſſibility of reſiſtance left, I reſolved to caſt my ſelf at the King my Maſters feet, and rather to be ſacrificed for his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, if his wiſdome, upon triall of mee, ſhould ſo order it, then to live with appearance of ſuch evill, either by putting
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:137065:8"/>
my ſelfe into the protection of the Enemy, or by any other way of flying from the Kings juſtice, deſert mine owne innocency. From hence then I went to <hi>Ludlow,</hi> and from <hi>Ludlow</hi> in like manner to <hi>Worceſter,</hi> profeſſing there my purpoſe to ride to <hi>Oxford.</hi> But ſickneſſe ſtaying me there a weeke untoucht, in comes my deputy Governour, and very unthankfully, being ſtirred up with a cauſeleſſe revenge, chargeth me with the loſſe of <hi>Hereford</hi> by treachery; which, if it were true, the Orders given and diligence uſed by mee, manifeſted in the foregoing Relation, would be a ſtrange peece of policie; for it is as cleare as the Sunne that if the inferiour officers upon whom this Relation in the face of the world, chargeth the loſſe of the place, had performed thoſe Orders, it had been impoſſible that the Town ſhould have been taken in this manner though I had concurred. For there would have beene an Alarum, and then, the Garriſon with the Towne and Gentry, would have made their defence ſufficiently, maugre the Governour. But I am charged, and muſt anſwer; you ſhall heare the proofes. It is ſaid that I received money for the delivering the Towne and Lieut: <hi>Wykes,</hi> who is a perſon that hath relation to my knowne Enemies, gives in evidence, that Mr. <hi>Charles Bridges</hi> did affirme to him, that about five or ſix dayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the loſſe of <hi>Hereford</hi> he brought ſixteene or ſeventeen hundred pounds to me for the delivery of the Towne.</p>
            <p>To cleare which, Mr. <hi>Charles Bridges</hi> hath diſclaimed it to ſeverall perſons of honour and quality. But then <hi>Wykes</hi> alleadgeth further that Mr. <hi>Thomas Pembridge,</hi> Collonell
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:137065:8"/>
               <hi>Morgans</hi> Secretary, ſaid to him, that he knew nothing of the ſaid ſeventeen hundred pounds; but that he had brought twelve hundred pounds from <hi>Glouceſter</hi> to the old <hi>Gore,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a little Village betweene <hi>Hereford</hi> and <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one of the Convoy, which money he ſaw told in <hi>Glou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter,</hi> and (to <hi>Wykes</hi> his beſt remembrance) ſaid it was for Sir <hi>Barnabas Scudamore</hi> for the delivery of <hi>Hereford;</hi> and that hee the ſaid <hi>Pembridge</hi> thought, that the Parliament would be glad, if Sir <hi>Barnabas Scudamore</hi> were put to death that they might pay him no more money. Now, if for one man to allege, that he heard another man, and another, ſay this and that thing, ſhall paſſe for good evidence in a judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall triall, or with juſt men; what innocency, what perſon can be ſafe? Beſides, for mine owne part, I that tender the good of my ſoule, and would not (however other things may goe with me) loſe my reputation with good men, by adding wilfull falſehood to theſe ſcandalls, do here ſolemnly proteſt before God and the world, that I never received from the Parliament, or any other perſon whatſoever, or treated with the Parliament, or any perſon whatſoever, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly or indirectly, for the delivery up of <hi>Hereford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Collonell <hi>Birches</hi> printed letter, upon the taking of <hi>Hereford</hi> to his ſuperiours in <hi>London,</hi> ſhews, that there were great disburſements made to ſeverall perſons, beſides deepe ingagements, upon their going on to <hi>Hereford:</hi> ſo that there were inſtruments enow to be ſatisfied more then this twelve hundred pounds would performe; and therefore, men need not muſe what imployment there ſhould be for this ſumme
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:137065:9"/>
though the Governour touched it not. Secondly, tis al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leged I had intelligence with the enemy: And for proofe of this there is produced a paper, wherein there were fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures and words at length, which they ſay were written by me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> Tis true, I confeſſe the ſcribling of ſuch a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; but not with thoſe thoughts as they would have it. To ſatisfie your deſires, the manner, thus:</p>
            <p>About a Moneth before the Towne was loſt, having been all day ſitting with the Commiſſioners of Array, and returning weary and melancholy to my Houſe, ſome little ſpace before ſupper time I found my Secretary writing in the Parlour, with divers others of my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; and taking one of his permes, I tore a peece of the backſide of a letter, which was foule too, and broken with the ſeale; and ſitting downe I began to ſuffer my pen to drop forth any thing that a melancholy fancie, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending nothing, might happen upon. So firſt I wrote three or four Arithmeticall figures, then three or foure wordes, then leaving a blanck ſpace I wrote againe words, and then figures, and ſo wordes interchangeably for ſome ſix lines, ſubſcribed with my name, and dated at <hi>Hereford,</hi> both written backward; and then againe my name written at large forward. By which time, hearing ſome company comming in to ſuppe with me, and knowing one of them to have an intention to procure a paſſe from <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> I ſuddainely foulded up this written characterized peece of paper, and endorſed it, (for Major
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:137065:9"/>
               <hi>Dobſon</hi> at <hi>Gloceſter</hi>) to give occaſion to the company and the aforeſaid Gentleman to exerciſe their witts and to make themſelves merry in deſciphering and giving ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifications to things that were altogether non-ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, and ſo left it careleſſely upon the Table for one of them to take up. Accordingly taken up it was by one of them, (Sir <hi>Baynham Throgmorton</hi> my Couſin Germane in the firſt degree) but it ſeemes with a falſe heart; who, inſteade of communicating it for ſporte, concealed it in his pocket; (though he could be contented to ſup with me that night,) and inſtead of revealing it Loyally to the King, with that diligence as the nature of ſuch an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faire did require, (it being in his apprehention, as is now pretended, intelligence with the enemy,) conceales it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a Moneth, till <hi>Hereford</hi> was loſt: And then, comes his unthankfull brother, Sir <hi>Nicholas Throgmorton</hi> my Deputie Governour, in a cauſeleſſe revenge (being for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly upon ſome difference with a perſon of quality, as well as he, confined by me) and bringes it with him to <hi>Worceſter;</hi> and by virtue of that nonſenſe-paper, princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally, laies this charge of Treachery upon me. But, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no intelligence can be held between two without communication, and that no conceipts of the minde can be communicated by non-ſignificant meanes, I hope this ſerowle will never be admitted as an evidence againſt the, untill that which is writ within, be firſt proved to ſignifie and intend ſuch intelligence as is preſumed. Now that by ſcribling or writing upon this paper there was my intention in me to ſend or communicate any thing
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:137065:10"/>
to Major <hi>Dobſon,</hi> I diſavow, and doe here againe affirme in the preſence of God, under the ſame Proteſtation, which I formerly made concerning Money, that it was not ſo much as conceived in my thoughts. Which yet if any man ſhould diſtruſt, I could produce a paper from Major <hi>Dobſon,</hi> though I never ſought it, in which under his owne hand, he doth upon the faith of a Gentleman, and the honour of a Soldier averre, that there hath never any letter, or character, paſſed from me to him, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the betraying of the Towne of <hi>Hereford.</hi> And theſe are the Columns upon which they have placed their charge of Treachery; namely, theſe two heare-ſaies, and this ſcrap of non-ſignificant paper.</p>
            <p>But here is not all: For beſides this Treachery, I am further charged with willfull negligence; and ſo exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned upon theſe particulars following.</p>
            <p>
               <label>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> 1.</label> Firſt tis alledged, that I commanded to have the Key of the Sally-port of St. <hi>Owens Gate,</hi> to ſend out a Party of Horſe, but did not.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Reſol.</label> Tis true, I intended to ſend forth a party of Horſe, in caſe an Alarum ſhould be given; but no Ala<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rum comming, no order was given to ſend out that way.</p>
            <p>
               <label>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> 2.</label> Secondly, they ſay, that a Knight in the Towne ſent two of his men in armes to have gone with the party of Horſe, but the Governour ſent them back with thankes, and ſaid he had ſent out a party already which was not ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:137065:10"/>
               <label>Reſ.</label> I grant there was no party ſent out; but that was Major <hi>Fletchers</hi> fault, not mine: for I gave Orders that afternoone, to him that commanded the Horſe in cheife, to ſend out a good party of Horſe, with a carefull Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, at Port ſhutting; which Order Major <hi>Fletcher,</hi> in his examination upon oath, confeſſeth to be charged upon him by the perſon commanding the Horſe in cheife: but, it is evident, theſe Orders were not obſerved by him. Now, I ſuppoſing Horſe to be ſent forth according to my Order &amp; no Alarum given, to what purpoſe ſhould I have ſent out that Gentlemans two Horſes? But the truth is I remember nothing of any ſuch offer made me.</p>
            <p>
               <label>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> 3.</label> Thirdly, tis ſaid, that Captain <hi>Fletcher,</hi> and one Maſter <hi>Terringham,</hi> after they had gone the grand round with me that night, deſired that they might goe forth, or ſend out a party of their Horſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Reſol.</label> But, this is as true as the reſt, and Major <hi>Flet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher</hi> in his examination only affirmes, that having gone the grand round, he asked me whether I would command him any further ſervice, expecting (he doth not ſay de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring) that I would have ſome of thoſe Horſe ſent out. To which queſtion, (apprehending it only as a civill ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of leave, not knowing that the Order of ſending forth Horſe at Port ſhutting was charged on him; nor having the leaſt ſuſpition that the ſaid Order was neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, and ſo no Horſe abroad) I anſwered, no more then the obſervance of their former Order; which was an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der requiring all Horſe in the Towne (excepting thoſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:137065:11"/>
that were upon the out-guard that night) to be ready by eight a clock the ſame morning, and ſo diſmiſſed them.</p>
            <p>
               <label>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> 4.</label> Fourthly, becauſe Livetenant <hi>Cooper,</hi> the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor of the Townes Livetenant, did fetch the keies of the Ports from my Houſe, and did ſo perfidiouſly open the Gate, at which the enemy entred, it is alledged (by the ſaid Major <hi>Chaplaine,</hi> to excuſe his owne palpable naughtineſſe) that I did know and allow of his Livete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant <hi>Cooper</hi> to open the Ports.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Reſol.</label> But this hath as much truth as the former: For to what end did the Towne commend, and I entertaine him to be Major, if his Livetenant could ſupply the place, and the truſt ſhould be repoſed in him? And theſe be the maine arguments, by which they would make me guilty of wilfull negligence. I confeſſe I am more then halfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to lengthen the Readers trouble in ſetting downe ſuch triviall things, eſpecially ſince none of theſe objections have been proved upon oath. Yet, having been interrogated upon them, I thought it not amiſſe for ſatisfaction, to produce them to the view of the world to meet with rumors, leſt they ſhould gaine cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to my prejudice.</p>
            <p>So, now you have ſeen both the charge and the proofs. The charge great enough, Treachery and Negligence: And the proofes weake enough, neither of them valid, even to the ordinary Reader. For as to the Charge of wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full negligence, none of the allegations above recited hath been made upon oath: but being ſent to the Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate Marſhall, he thought it not amiſſe to heare what I
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:137065:11"/>
could anſwer to them.</p>
            <p>And as to the charge of treachery they have only offered as I ſaid before, two heare-ſaies and a ſcrap of non-ſignificant paper. Yet I have laine long enough a priſoner at <hi>Worceſtor</hi> for depoſitions to have been ſent in, if matter could have been as readily found as my adverſaries have been laborious and curious to hunt after it.</p>
            <p>But how unlikely is it, that my deſires ſhould any wayes concurre in this fact, ſeeing the loſſe of that place hath not only put my life, but my good name, more precious then life, to moſt eminent hazard? By this meanes, <hi>I</hi> am depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not onely of the honour of being Governour, and the benefit accruing by that command; but of all meanes of ſatisfaction for proviſions of my owne, which were in the towne, before the time of my being Governour, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by my Commiſſary to the Garriſon, amounting to the value of 700 and odde pounds; of all hopes of reliefe for my other ingagements and disburſements to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſarie for the Garriſon, amounting to as much more by the Commiſſaries Accompts; of all ſtores of proviſions, &amp; arreares of my allowance for my own houſe: Not to ſpeak of my intertainment money, horſes, plate, and houſhold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuffe, ſurmounting in all the ſumme of 3000l. Beſides, the eſtates of my friends, and of my beſt friends in that County, in which was included the onely meanes remayning for my ſubſiſtence, was heereby expoſed to Sequeſtration: the many noble and worthy perſons of both ſexes, whom I loved and honoured, who had fled thither for their laſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:137065:12"/>The Towne, in which I had ſome part of my Educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and whereof I was now a ſworne member: my fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Citizens and companions in Loyalty, that ſo bravely aſſiſted me in the late ſiege againſt a formidable Army of Scots; all theſe were made lyable (I ſhould deteſt to live, if by me) to the mercy of a party which eſteemed us, as of all others moſt malignant, ſo moſt worthy of extream ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. And all this, for what? for twelve, or ſeventeen hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounds? why, you ſee by that above mentioned, that I ſhould have been ſo a loſer in point of money. And if it be replyed that I ſhould have received more afterward; I pray you reflect, that the way to <hi>Oxford,</hi> was not the way to that. The blood of ancient Gently, and of an untain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted family, makes me abhorre the firſt apprehenſions of ſo deteſtable and damnable a fact. For no act can bee more perfectly baſe &amp; cowardly, then, for feare of any temporall want, to deſert in this ſort, Iuſtice, Honour, and Humanity. Let my carriage be conſidered before, and after this action. Take a view of the whole courſe of my life, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly in this warre. Looke upon the orders I gave even to the laſt, while this evill fortune was in motion Regard my behaviour ſince, putting my ſelfe, ſtript of all aſſiſtance, into the power of the Kings party, inraged like Lions with that loſſe; and doth not my behaviour in theſe diſtinct parts of time, adminiſter juſt arguments of innocency and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy?</p>
            <p>But not to tire the Reader, this was done by externall force, and therefore it needs not be conſidered what reaſon
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:137065:12"/>
or what affection might carry me, for it was done by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and in no wiſe by me. Briefly, you ſee my diligence was ſuch in point of intelligence, that wee had continuall notice of the motions of the Enemy, till the Horſe were to got forth at Port-ſhutting that VVedneſday night; and the failing of their going forth was not through default of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from me. Then, upon the intelligence, orders were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently given out, and continually renewed by mee, to the Major of the Towne, Captaine <hi>Chaplaine,</hi> to double the guards within. And drawing the Horſe in, I commanded them double duty, that is, to guard as well without as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Towne. Vpon the ſaid VVedneſday in the afternoon as ſoone as the notice of the Enemies advance came to mee, I imparted it immediatly to Mr. <hi>Major,</hi> and publiſhed it by Proclamation to the whole Towne. At nine a clocke that night, I diſmiſt the Towne Major <hi>Chaplaine</hi> to his reſt, that he might be with me at five next morning to take care of the Towne. <hi>I</hi> went the Grand Round, not remiſſly; but correcting faults as <hi>I</hi> paſſed: I ſent for Captaine <hi>Traherne</hi> Captaine of the watch to come to the place of his duty, the Maine Guard: At every Port, I charged them upon paine of death, that neither Officer nor Soulder ſhould flirre off their guard, ever inculcating, that the Enemy was advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, and the Towne in danger. I Cudgelled the drunken Corporall at <hi>Byſters</hi> Gate, commanding him to be ſet by the heels, and that an officer in Commiſſion ſhould bee placed at that Port. <hi>I</hi> viewed the Centries Armes that ſtood over that Gate, and added another Centrie to him, directing the Centries ſhould be viſited and relieved every halfe houre.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:137065:13"/>
At the diſmiſſing the Guards, I charged <hi>Ballard</hi> to continue Rounds, without ceaſing, untill eight a clocke in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and then to bring me an account.</p>
            <p>Permit me this further, that I was ſo farre from giving order (as is reported) that the Gates ſhould bee opened at 8. a clock, that I intended they ſhould be kept ſhut at leaſt till ten. For having received private notice that ſome oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was like to be made by Towneſmen, in defence of the Mutiniers to be tried; I was willing, that buſineſſe ſhould be ended, before the Gates were unlocked. And my reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on being, immediatly after the riſing of the Court of VVar, to march out my ſelfe in perſon with the whole body of Horſe, to diſcover, and obſerve the motions of the Enemy, I truely meant the ports ſhould not be opened till <hi>I</hi> went forth my ſelfe. And of this reſolution of mine, Liev. Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell <hi>Ieffreyes</hi> is a perfect witneſſe; to whom <hi>I</hi> did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate it, upon Letters <hi>I</hi> had received the day before, from Sir <hi>Michael Woodhouſe</hi> Governour of <hi>Ludlow,</hi> who ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected the Enemy had a deſigne to plant a Garriſon at <hi>Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> to ſtop the intercourſe betweene <hi>Ludlow</hi> and <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you ſee how my intention was made fruſtrate: my ſervant that waited upon me in my chamber, ſtealing away the keyes (as he might no leſſe eaſily have taken away my life) from the place (where and in places like to which all Governours uſe to confide their keyes) they uſually reſted, and ſafely enough even during the late ſiege; though <hi>I</hi> will not charge my ſaid ſervant with any knowledge of Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant <hi>Coopers</hi> treacherous purpoſe. And this is the negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence that I am guilty of. Now if any of theſe orders
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:137065:13"/>
had been fully executed, could this Towne have been loſt? It cannot be imagined. On the other ſide, you ſee how the plot was laid and Carried. <hi>Sir Iohn Bridges</hi> and Colonell <hi>Birch,</hi> riding into <hi>Hereford ſhire,</hi> receive information of the preſent ſtate of <hi>Hereford,</hi> by Captaine <hi>Howorth</hi> and Captain <hi>Alderne:</hi> theſe two, with the addition of Captaine <hi>Ballard</hi> my Lievtenant, conveyed continuall intelligence to <hi>Gloce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</hi> Major <hi>Fletcher</hi> omits to ſend forth out guards: Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor <hi>Chaplaine</hi> failes to double the guards within; and, in a word, keeping his bed, neglects the whole duty naturally inherent in the place of Major. Captain <hi>Treherne,</hi> Captain of the watch, comes not at all to the maine Guard. Captain Lievtenant <hi>Ballard,</hi> commanding the guards, drawes off the guards from Byſters Gate, in order to his diſabling be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehand the murthering Peece. Lievtenant <hi>Cooper</hi> opens the great gate, lets downe the chaine, lets downe the draw bridge, and gives the word, <hi>Now, or Never;</hi> with which the Enemy enters, with three or foure and twenty hundred; accompanied with Captaine <hi>Howorth, Sir Iohn Bridges,</hi> and Captaine <hi>Alderne:</hi> And yet the whole buſineſſe ſtill lay upon me: although, by this time, it is very well knowne what it coſt the Parliament, and who received their moneyes.</p>
            <p>This is the truth: and <hi>I</hi> doubt not, but it will finde credit with good men, and abundantly ſatisfie the generous and judicious ſpirits in order to my innocency, and deliver mee from the falſe &amp; foule charge of Treachery or Negligence. My conſcience bearing witneſſe with me, that I am guilty only of the unhappineſſe of it; which hath been, and is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all men, of honor, of my profeſſion, <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
